{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>This group began a revolt by symbolically overturning the cauldrons in the Meat Quarter.</em> Members of this group were taught in the Enderun school. The Sekbans led the Jelali revolts against this group, and this group was targeted by the Nizam-i Cedid reforms. Mahmud II suppressed this group following the Auspicious Incident. This group was maintained through the Devsirme (<b>pr. dev-SHEER-may</b>), or \"blood tax.\" For the point, name this elite military group primarily made up of converted Christians which served the Ottoman sultans.", "answer": "<b><u>Janissaries</u></b> [or <b><u>Janissary</u></b> Corp; or <b><u>yeniceri</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>Mayor Fletcher Bowron said this event was mostly carried out by Southerners.</em> After this event, Senator Jack Tenney's Committee called the National Lawyers Guild \"Communists\" and blamed Nazis for it. Governor Earl Warren ordered the McGucken Committee to investigate this event's causes. Tensions were high prior to it because of the Sleepy Lagoon murder case the year before. In the lead-up to this event, police officers known as the \"Vengeance Squad\" and others stripped \"pachucos\" of their clothing. For the point, name these 1943 disturbances in Los Angeles in which white sailors attacked flamboyantly dressed Latino youths.", "answer": "<b><u>Zoot Suit</u></b> Riots  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>Jia Yi claimed that this dynasty collapsed because it did not alter its style of government after</em> <em>taking power</em>. A work about the Ten Crimes of this dynasty criticized it using Confucian reasoning. This dynasty\u2019s chancellor Li Si standardized the written Chinese script. The statesman Shang Yang made many legal reforms to this dynasty, which helped it end the Warring States period. This dynasty\u2019s first emperor unified China, but soon after his death it was overthrown by the Han. For the point, which Chinese dynasty was ruled by Shi Huangdi?", "answer": "<b><u>Qin</u></b> Dynasty (pr. \u201cChin\u201d \u2013 do NOT accept pr. \u201cChing\u201d)  {II}", "metadata": "TR"}, {"question": "<em>After a player left one of these teams for the other, he had a pig\u2019s head thrown at him during a</em> <em>game</em>. Following the Hungarian Revolution, these two teams signed players such as Zolt\u00e1n Czibor (<b>pr. CHEE-boar</b>) and Ferenc Pusk\u00e1s. After one of these teams signed Alfredo di Stefano, he instead played for the other after the interference of their country\u2019s dictator. One of these teams\u2019 slogan \u201c<em>Mes Que Un Club</em>\u201d signifies its support of Catalan culture, while the other was the favorite club of Francisco Franco. For the point, which two Spanish soccer teams currently feature rivals Cristiano Ronaldo and Lionel Messi?", "answer": "<b><u>Real Madrid</u></b> C.F. and F.C. <b><u>Barcelona</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Madrid</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "TR"}, {"question": "<em>At this event, Robert Stockton made an unfortunate joke about \"plenty of living bodies to</em> <em>replace the dead ones.\"</em> This event's problems were caused by the failure to repeat the tests made on an object called the \"Orator.\" Shortly after this event, Julia Gardiner became engaged to President John Tyler. This event resulted in the death of Secretary of State Abel Upshur after a demonstration of the \"Peacemaker\" went awry. For the point, name this 1844 disaster in which a naval gun exploded, killing two Cabinet members.", "answer": "USS <em><b><u>Princeton</u></b></em> disaster  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>A process posited by this theory was the subject of the ABC paper.</em> An event predicted by this theory was followed by a period of time during which the gravitational force was as strong as the other fundamental forces, known as the Planck epoch. During a radio broadcast, the name for this theory was coined by Fred Hoyle, who actually opposed Georges LeMaitres\u2019 idea of it. Evidence for this theory came from the linear relationship between redshift and distance posited by Edwin Hubble. For the point, name this scientific theory that suggests the universe was born from a singularity.", "answer": "<b><u>Big Bang</u></b> [prompt on the \u201c<b><u>start of the universe</u></b>\u201d or such equivalents]  {II}", "metadata": "Ike"}, {"question": "<em>This event\u2019s namesake establishment was operated by the \u201cFat Tony\u201d Lauria of the Genovese</em> <em>crime family, which often blackmailed the establishment\u2019s patrons.</em> Participators in this event sang a parody of the \u201cHowdy Doody\u201d theme song entitled \u201cWe are the Village Girls.\u201d This event was sparked by an NYPD liquor raid. President Obama mentioned this event with Seneca Falls and Selma in his second inaugural address. For the point, identify this 1969 riot at the namesake New York bar that marked the beginning of the modern gay rights movement.", "answer": "<b><u>Stonewall</u></b> Uprising  {II}", "metadata": "ED"}, {"question": "<em>A play titled for this man is sometimes called \u201cthe power of God\u201d and was written by Jean</em> <em>Anouilh.</em> This man\u2019s death is partly caused by William Hamleigh at the end of Ken Follett\u2019s novel <em>The Pillars of the Earth</em>. This man rejects power, fame, glory and physical safety from four tempters in a T.S. Eliot play in which he is murdered by four knights. Pilgrims journey to visit this man\u2019s shrine in a collection of poems by Geoffrey Chaucer. For the point, name this archbishop of Canterbury who was supposedly murdered on orders from Henry II.", "answer": "Thomas \u00e0 <b><u>Becket</u></b>", "metadata": "Ike"}, {"question": "<em>This man gave a cardinalship to Guillame Briconnet, who later gained the Bishophric of</em> <em>Nimes (<b>pr. NEEM</b>)</em>. Among this man's mistresses was Vannozza dei Cattanei, with whom he sired his most notable children. Johann Burchard claimed that he held the Banquet of Chestnuts. He made a controversial move in adding twelve cardinals to the College of Cardinals, including one of his sons. His enemies accused him of committing incest with his daughter Lucrezia. For the point, what corrupt pope was, like Callixtus III, a member of the Borgia family?", "answer": "Pope <b><u>Alexander VI</u></b> [or <b><u>R</u></b>odrigo Lanzol de <b><u>Borgi</u></b>a; prompt on <b><u>Borgia</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>The deeds of two members of these people were detailed by the monk Geoffrey Malaterra.</em> These people were given permanent territory in the Treaty of Saint-Clair-sur-Epte, in which their leader Rollo pledge himself to Charles the Simple. The Hauteville family were members of this group, who conquered areas like Apulia and Calabria. One of these people named Roger established a kingdom in Sicily, while his brother Robert Guiscard ruled southern Italy. Other members of this group conquered England after winning the Battle of Hastings. For the point, identify this group named for the region ruled by William the Conqueror.", "answer": "<b><u>Norman</u></b>s  {II}", "metadata": "SL"}, {"question": "<em>This man debated G.K. Chesterton in the 1931 Mecca Temple debate on religion</em>. While in Detroit, this man gave the 1925 speech known as the \"I Believe in the Law of Love\" oration in support of Dr. Ossian Sweet. He angered a rival by sarcastically asking questions about where Cain obtained his wife or the truth about Adam's rib. This man's 12 hour long plea managed to save the lives of the \"thrill killers\" Leopold and Loeb. He asked questions to William Jennings Bryan about the Bible's \"literal\" nature. For the point, name this lawyer who defended John Scopes in the \"Monkey Trial.\"", "answer": "Clarence <b><u>Darrow</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This adjective was first applied to a historical event by a female economist who signed many</em> <em>articles with the name \u201cAdam Smith,\u201d and served as ambassador to the United States.</em> Following an event known by this adjective, different stamps were affixed to old <em>koruna</em> banknotes, and Vladimir Meciar (<b>pr. METZ-ee-ar</b>) came to power. During an earlier event described by this adjective, the Civic Forum was established following the resignation of Gustav Husak and the democratic election of president Vaclav Havel. For the point, name this English adjective prefixing a 1993 \u201cDivorce\u201d that split, and a 1989 \u201cRevolution\u201d that liberalized, Czechoslovakia in a gentle way.", "answer": "<b><u>velvet</u></b> [or <b><u>Velvet</u></b> Divorce; or <b><u>Velvet</u></b> Revolution]  {II}", "metadata": "AG"}, {"question": "<em>This writer\u2019s best known work about the sea includes a chapter called \u201cThe Birth of an</em> <em>island\u201d and is titled The Sea Around Us</em>. Monsanto responded to a work by this author by publishing the pamphlet, \u201cThe Desolate Year.\u201d That work by this author describes takes its title from John Keats\u2019 line, \u201cThe sedge has wither\u2019d from the lake, And no birds sing.\u201d This author is most notable for a book that inspired the banning of DDT. For 10 point, name this author of <em>Silent Spring</em>.", "answer": "Rachel <b><u>Carson</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "Ike"}, {"question": "<em>One party recovered the Colonia da Sacramento, land in present day Uruguay, in these</em> <em>treaties.</em> Lingering issues in them were resolved by the later Treaties of Rastatt and Baden. In these treaties, one party received the Asiento, a monopoly on South American slave trade. Britain received Newfoundland and gained parts of Rupert\u2019s Land from the French in these treaties. As a result of these treaties, Philip of Anjou became king of Spain but renounced any claim to the French throne. For the point, name this series of treaties signed in 1713 which ended the War of the Spanish Succession.", "answer": "Peace/Treaty of <b><u>Utrecht</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>Before taking on this occupation, a Scottish man set up a socialist cooperative near Monona,</em> <em>Iowa</em>. The most famous man with this job in the Confederacy was George S. Cook. Another man with this job ran ads urging young Union soldiers to become clients in order to acquire a memento for their parents. That man with this occupation staged an October 1862 exhibition \"The Dead of Antietam\" displaying Civil War carnage. For the point, name this occupation held by artist Matthew Brady.", "answer": "<b><u>photographer</u></b> [or <b><u>photojournalist</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This non-Christian god's name and symbol were incorporated into the Voortrekker</em> <em>monument in Pretoria, South Africa</em>. Scholars sometimes compare Psalm 104 to an earlier \"Great Hymn\" dedicated to this deity, inscribed on the tomb of Ai. Horemheb opposed worship of this deity. According to Sigmund Freud, this deity's chief promulgator was a close relative of Moses. Amarna was the main site of worship of this god, who was symbolized by a disk with rays shooting down from it. For the point, name this unitary solar god briefly imposed by the New Kingdom pharaoh first known as Amenhotep IV.", "answer": "<b><u>Aten</u></b> [or Ra-Horakhty-<b><u>Aten</u></b>; or <b><u>Aton</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on \u201cAmon\u201d or \"Ra\"; do not accept or prompt on \"Horus\"; do not accept \"Akhenaten\"]  {II}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em>This politician labeled Medal of Honor winning opponent Leo K. Thorsness a</em> <em>\"carpetbagger.\"</em> Late in life, this man started an inn in Connecticut, and admitted its failure taught him lessons about small business that would have helped him in the Senate. He said \"This chamber reeks of blood\" in support of his bill sponsored with Mark Hatfield to end the Vietnam War. This man was forced to drop Thomas Eagleton from the ticket after the latter's history of shock therapy became public. For the point, name this South Dakota Senator who lost the 1972 presidential election to Richard Nixon.", "answer": "George <b><u>McGovern</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This country established a woman\u2019s right to an abortion if her pregnancy is life-threatening</em> <em>in the 1992 \u201cX case.\u201d</em> The financial genius Sean Lemass was elected Minister of Supplies in this country during its period of official neutrality during World War II called \u201cThe Emergency.\u201d This country became a republic in 1937, following a period of fifteen years in which it was a \u201cFree State,\u201d during which the conservative \u201cFianna Fail\u201d party was founded. Following its economic boom in the 1990s, this country was called the \u201cCeltic Tiger.\u201d For the point, name this predominantly-Catholic country that occupies most of an island west of Britain.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Ireland</u></b> [or Poblacht na h<b><u>Eire</u></b>ann]  {II}", "metadata": "AG"}, {"question": "<em>This man introduced words like \"powwow\" and \"papoose\" to English with his</em> \u201c<em>A Key Into</em> <em>the Language of America</em>\u201d. This man supported the signers of the Portsmouth Compact, including William Coddington. He wrote a dialogue between Truth and Peace which sparked a pamphlet war with John Cotton and attacks a \"Bloody Tenent\". This man signed treaties with the Narragansett Indians and welcomed Anne Hutchinson to his colony. For the point, name this supporter of religious toleration who founded Providence Plantations, a colony that would become Rhode Island.", "answer": "Roger <b><u>Williams</u> </b> {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>This monarch ended the use of Sandringham clocks.</em> An attempt on this ruler's life was made by Jerome Bannigan. After joining the 1st Battalion of the Grenadier Guards, this man complained to Lord Kitchener about not being sent directly into combat. This man was heavily suspected of being a Nazi sympathizer after he and his wife visited Adolf Hitler in 1937. He gained the title of Duke of Windsor after his brother, the Duke of York, took the name George VI. For the point, what British king abdicated the throne in order to marry Wallis Simpson?", "answer": "King <b><u>Edward VIII</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>MONY Life Insurance Company investigator K.B. Ponder concluded this event was an</em> <em>accident.</em> This event resulted in a funeral administered by Christian Nationalist Gerald L.K. Smith. The man who carried out this event was the son-in-law of Judge Benjamin Henry Pavy, who was about to be the victim of a redistricting plan. Its perpetrator was shot 62 times by bodyguards, with some speculating those shots killed the guards' boss. This event was carried out at the State Capitol by Dr. Carl Weiss. For the point, name this September 10, 1935, murder of a Louisiana Senator known as the \"Kingfish.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Assassination</u></b> of Huey Pierce <b><u>Long</u></b> Jr. [accept words like <b><u>murder</u></b> for \u201cassassination\u201d]  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>During a campaign centered on this country, Mount Matajur's seven thousand defenders</em> <em>were defeated by Erwin Rommel's one hundred men.</em> As a result of a battle in this country, David Lloyd George proposed the formation of a Supreme War Council. An incredibly nationalist poet from this country took over the city of Fiume (<b>pr. fee-OO-may</b>), ignoring the Treaty of Rapallo. Twelve battles in this country were fought alongside the Isonzo River. This country signed an armistice with Austria-Hungary after defeating them at Vittorio Veneto. For the point, name this home country of Gabriele d'Annunzio and setting of the Battle of Caporetto.", "answer": "<b><u>Italy</u></b> [or <b><u>Italian</u></b> Republic; or Repubblica <b><u>Italiana</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>The prototypes of this product were named \"Rocky,\" \"Skip,\" and \"Ace.\"</em> This product shares its name with a 1945 movie that was the life story of reporter Ernie Pyle. Its copyrighted features include a scar on its right cheek. A variant of this thing in England was called \"Action Man.\" By the late 1960's, this thing was marketed as an \"Adventurer\" to avoid anti-Vietnam War backlash. Hasbro was reluctant to sell this thing because marketers thought boys would not play with dolls.  For the point, name this action figure, a \"real American hero\" that is a miniature soldier.", "answer": "<b><u>G.I. Joe</u></b> [or <b><u>America\u2019s Movable Fighting Man</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>Joe</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>Manetho relates how an army of these people led by the Moses-like priest Osarseph ravaged</em> <em>Egypt.</em> A statue in Angkor Thom supposedly depicts King Yasovarman as one of these people. Hagioscope windows in churches were designed for these people. A king who was succeeded by Guy of Lusignan, Baldwin IV, was one of these people. Father Damian worked in a colony of these people on the island of Molokai. For the point, name these people who were historically shunned for having a contagious, disfiguring skin disease.", "answer": "<b><u>leper</u></b>s [or people with <b><u>leprosy</u></b>; or people with <b><u>Hansen</u></b>'s Disease]  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>After being given a 300-page report related to this day, Daniel Patrick Moynihan threw it to</em> <em>the ground and stomped on it.</em> A song about this day begins \"it doesn't make much sense\u2026there ought to be a law against anyone who takes offense\" to celebrating it. A debate about this day led to the moving of the 1993 Super Bowl from Arizona after that state rejected celebrating it. Jesse Helms filibustered over the creation of this holiday, saying it honored a Communist. For the point, name this holiday celebrated on the third Monday of January to honor a civil rights leader.", "answer": "<b><u>Martin Luther King</u></b> Jr. Day [or <b><u>MLK</u></b> Day; or <b><u>Birthday of Martin Luther King</u> </b>Jr.]  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>The Synod of Bishops was established at this event.</em> It opened with the declaration \u201cGaudet mater Ecclesia.\u201d Sedevacantists opposed this council. <em>Gaudium et Spes</em> was one of the four Apostolic Constitutions arising from this event which also produced the Dogmatic Constitution <em>Lumen Gentium</em>. This council controversially absolved Jews of guilt for the death of Jesus in <em>Nostra Aetate (<b>pr. eye-TAH-tay</b>)</em>. For the point, name this Church council, convoked by John XXIII and continued by Paul VI, which allowed for the use of the vernacular in mass, among other liberalizing reforms.", "answer": "<b><u>Second Vatican</u></b> Council [or <b><u>Vatican II</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>One area of this city has been nicknamed Little Kurdistan for having the highest population</em> <em>of Kurds in the US</em>. Its Bridgestone Arena was the site of a 2010 benefit concert after flooding caused billions of dollars of damage along the Cumberland River. A trail which ends in this city and begins in Natchez, Mississippi was the site of the death of Meriwether Lewis. This city is both the namesake of an acclaimed film directed by Robert Altman and a recent ABC series. It contains the Country Music Hall of Fame and is the site of regular performances at the Grand Ole Opry. For the point, name this large city in Central Tennessee.", "answer": "<b><u>Nashville</u></b>, Tennessee  {II}", "metadata": "EA"}, {"question": "<em>This man was named Lord of Ireland, but was forced to leave after offending local chiefs by</em> <em>pulling on their long beards</em>. While king, this man attempted a combined land and water attack to relieve the siege of Chateau Gaillard (<b>pr. guy-ARD</b>). This man\u2019s allies lost the Battle of Bouvines, and he lost much of the Angevin Empire to Philip Augustus. He allegedly murdered his nephew Arthur of Brittany and at the Battle of Mirabeau he rescued his mother Eleanor of Aquitaine. For the point, name this son of Henry II and brother of Richard I who was forced to sign the Magna Carta.", "answer": "King <b><u>John</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Lackland</u></b>]", "metadata": "TR"}, {"question": "<em>The platoon system was introduced to these institutions as part of William Wirt's Gary Plan.</em> These institutions were the subject of the Massachusetts Bay Colony's Old Deluder Satan Act. A product created by William Holmes McGuffey was widely used in these institutions. Section 16 of each township under the Land Ordinance of 1785 was reserved for one of these institutions. These institutions were where the Blue-back Spellers of Noah Webster were used. For the point, name these institutions for which Horace Mann advocated, places where children are educated.", "answer": "public <b><u>school</u></b>s [do not accept \"colleges\" or \"universities\"]  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>This person may have been mockingly called \u201cSquill-head\u201d on account of his unusually</em> <em>large head.</em> This ostracizer of Cimon was mentored by Ephialtes (<b>pr. eff-EYE-ul-teez</b>). This person spearheaded the adoption of the Megaran Decree, which prompted a conflict where he put trust in the walls of the city and the navy. He person gave a famous funeral oration and helped construct the Parthenon. For the point, name this Athenian leader who died of the plague, ending the first portion of the Peloponnesian wars.", "answer": "<b><u>Pericles</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>The highest ranked target of this event, which also caused the deaths of Tyrone Woods and</em> <em>Glen Doherty, died of smoke inhalation on a bathroom floor.</em> The alleged organizer of this event, Ahmed Abu Khattala was captured by Special Forces in June, 2014. Trey Gowdy of South Carolina is leading the investigation of it. One person almost had her career derailed due to statements she made after this event on talk shows attributing it to the film \u201cInnocence of Muslims.\u201d That person is Susan Rice. For the point, name this event which led to the death of American Ambassador Christopher Stevens in Libya.", "answer": "Terrorist attack on American Embassy in <b><u>Benghazi</u></b> [or <b><u>Benghazigate</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>This composer\u2019s Prelude #20 in C minor was dubbed \u201cFuneral March\u201d by Hans von Bulow.</em> The final piece of this composer\u2019s Opus 10 was popularly considered to be a response to the failed November Uprising. An A major work of his subtitled \u201cMilitary\u201d was played daily on his home country\u2019s radio in protest of Nazi invaders. This pianist, who emigrated to Paris as a young man, popularized a form invented by John Field, the nocturne. For the point, what composer and pianist\u2019s mazurkas and polonaises paid tribute to his native Poland?", "answer": "Frederic Francois <b><u>Chopin</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em>One leader was interviewed during this conflict by the</em> New York Times\u2019<em> Herbert Matthews</em>. During this conflict, Camilo Cienfuegos became known as the \u201cHero of Yaguajay\u201d. One side in this conflict set up <em>Radio Rebelde</em> to broadcast propaganda. The leader of one side in this conflict had created the 26th of July Movement after a failed attack on the Moncada Barracks. This conflict ended after the Battle of Santa Clara, when dictator Fulgencio Batista fled the country. For the point, which conflict saw its namesake island nation taken over by Fidel Castro?", "answer": "<b><u>Cuban Revolution</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "TR"}, {"question": "<em>In the early twentieth century, this man lived at Skibo Castle</em>. A chief lieutenant and successor of this man was the \"master hustler,\" Charles M. Schwab. In 1901, he was named Lord Rector of the University of St. Andrews, a school he heavily supported. This man denounced \"the selfish millionaire\" who dies rich in an article explaining why he helped fund numerous libraries across the country. This author of the article, \"The Gospel of Wealth,\" eventually sold his company for $480 million in 1901 to J.P. Morgan. For the point, name this Scottish American founder of a steel company.", "answer": "Andrew <b><u>Carnegie</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>In this year, the Russian governor of Wallachia accepted the Proclamation of Islaz.</em> This year also featured the Five Days of Milan, which occurred after Ferdinand II granted the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies a new constitution. The Frankfurt Assembly convened in this year, and Lajos Kossuth\u2019s movement for Hungarian independence prompted Metternich to flee Vienna. This was also the year when King Louis-Philippe was deposed and the French Second Republic was established. For the point, name this \u201cyear of revolutions\u201d in 19th-century Europe.", "answer": "<b><u>1848</u></b>  {II}  <b>Extra Tossup \u2013 ONLY READ IF YOU BOTCH A QUESTION!</b> <em>A class of people known as calatores served people with this occupation</em>. Some people with this occupation marked out a certain area of the sky with a <em>lituus.</em> The right to hold this occupation was extended to the plebeians by the Lex Ogulnia. These people used a sacrificial knife called a <em>secespita</em>. A specific group of these people swore an oath of virginity and maintained a sacred fire in the temple of Vesta. The Pontifex Maximus was the leader of these people. For the point, name this occupation held by the Romans who facilitated religious ceremonies.  ANSWER: Roman <b><u>priest</u></b>s/<b><u>priestess</u></b>es [accept <b><u>augur</u></b>s, <em><b><u>flamines</u></b></em>, or <em><b><u>Vestales</u></b></em><b><u>/Vestal Virgins</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "SH"}], "bonuses": []}